This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
All right, let's um
let's get back to the subject at hand,
which is classical mechanics. No,
classical field theory.
But
classical field theory, as I've
emphasized several times, is a special
case of the general rules of classical
mechanics.
And that's the way it should be thought
of.
Uh as a um as an example, not maybe the
primary example
of uh the basic rules of classical
mechanics.
So
I think we have to
review just a little bit about classical
mechanics and then apply it in the field
theory context. I What I particularly
want to get through tonight
is the connection between
symmetries and conservation laws. Now,
we've done that in the context of
classical mechanics,
but it's especially interesting and
really takes
um
sort of front seat
in the subject of uh
relativistic field theory, the
connections between
symmetries and conservation laws.
So, let's go back a few steps
and review a little bit about classical
mechanics.
Least action, Lagrangian,
and conservation laws in the simple
context. I don't think we'll have to do
Hi, come in.
Uh I don't think we'll have to get too
involved with Hamiltonian mechanics
tonight, although later on we'll want
to.
But let's just review very quickly the
mechanics of a system of particles.
And uh for our purposes right now, we
could have just one particle
moving in one dimension, although
everything I say
uh could be generalized just by putting
a little index I next to some symbols.
I'll probably do that.
All right, so we have a particle
with a coordinate X.
Incidentally,
sometimes I use Q for coordinate,
sometimes I use X. I'll try to be
clearer about the
the logic if and if I change symbols,
ask me about it if it confuses you, but
I think probably it won't too much.
Anyway,
particle is described by a coordinate X,
which depends on time.
Of course, there could be N particles
and they could have three-dimensional
positions, in which case we would just
put a little I downstairs to indicate
which coordinate we were talking about.
And the object of a problem of mechanics
is to compute the orbit.
Vertically, as always, we put time.
Horizontally, we put X.
Uh however many X coordinates we need,
but I'll just draw one. And then the
particle moves
through space-time along some orbit
according to the principle of least
action.
And the principle of least action says
minimize or at least make stationary.
I'll describe what I mean by stationary
in a minute.
For our purposes, it can mean minimize.
Minimize the action, and the action is
the integral
of the Lagrangian, which depends on the
coordinates and the velocities. X dot
stands for dX dT
integrated with respect to time.
Uh
and just to remind you,
we hold the end points fixed.
And require
that this quantity is minimized.
Minimize with respect to what? Whenever
you say something's minimized, you
imagine that you can explore some space
of possibilities,
and then
minimizing means find the possibility
which gives you the minimum value of the
action in this case.
So, we're talking about exploring
different trajectories.
But in particular, let's make a little
change in the trajectory.
Some small change in the trajectory. The
small change in the trajectory could
involve a change from beginning to end,
or it could just involve some uh small
little region here where the trajectory
is changed.
And recalculate the action.
Recalculate the action as it deviates
from its value along the true
trajectory, and then require that uh
that when we vary the trajectory a
little bit, that the action always
increases. Now,
assuming that it increases really is
basically the same as assuming that it
doesn't change. Let me just remind you,
when you're minimizing a quantity, for
example, supposing you're minimizing
something with respect to one variable,
only one variable now. In this context,
we're minimizing with respect to an
infinite number of variables. The
infinite number of variables are all the
positions along the entire trajectory.
So, it's a very complicated problem of
minimization,
where we're minimizing with respect to
an infinite number of variables. But
nevertheless,
let's uh examine the problem of
minimizing something with respect to one
variable first.
All right, so let's say
a quantity, in this case, let's just
call it Let's call the quantity F,
and it could be F of some variable X,
and it's minimized at that point over
here. So, as you well know, the rule for
finding a minimum is just to
differentiate X
and set it equal to zero.
Another way to say the same thing is to
require that at this point here, that if
we make a little shift of X,
a little shift of X, then that the
change in F, the change of F,
delta F, when we change X a little bit,
should be zero.
That's the statement that it's the same
as the statement that the derivative is
zero,
that the change is equal to zero.
Okay? In both directions, no matter
which way you move.
If that's the case that the change is
zero,
zero, of course, means only for very,
very small excursions.
All right? So, the first order change
should be equal to zero. That's the same
as saying dF by dX is equal to zero.
We could also say that the change in F
when you move X a little bit, is the
derivative of F with respect to X
times delta X.
If dF by dX is equal to zero, so is
delta F. All right, so you get the idea.
Now, supposing uh you have many
variables. In particular, let's suppose
we have two variables. So, there's
another variable sticking out of the
blackboard here. And again, we have some
function which now depends on two
variables. Let's say X and Y.
And we're looking for some hole, some uh
some dip in the function where it
achieves its minimum with respect to
both variations in both directions.
In fact, we're looking for a place
where, no matter what direction we move
off in,
the function doesn't change
to first order.
That's The word for that is finding the
stationary points of the function, but a
particular example is finding the
minimum of a function.
Uh if we found the minimum of a function
with respect to all variations of this
point,
then what we want is that the derivative
that all the derivatives of F with
respect to X equal zero, with respect to
Y equal zero.
Or a shorthand version for it
is that if we're right at that point and
we vary both X and Y, or all of the
variables, whatever the variables are,
that the change in F
again should vanish. That's a shorthand
version for saying that all the
derivatives
are equal to zero.
So, in the same manner,
if we're looking for the
minimum of the action,
what we want to do is we want to explore
nearby trajectories. We think we have a
solution. This is supposed to be a
solution. We think we have a solution.
We want to explore nearby trajectories
and require that the change in the
action is zero when we make a small
change in trajectory.
Let's just write that the variation
of L
of X and X dot dT
is equal to zero when we change the
trajectory a little bit. Now, what does
changing the trajectory a little bit
mean?
It means we add to F to X of T, we add a
small change. X of T was supposed to be
the original solution.
Let's add something small
called epsilon
times an arbitrary function of T.
What are the variables in this problem
that we're minimizing with respect to?
We're minimizing with respect to all
these variables, f of t, f of t1, f of
t2. In fact, f
all along here. This little bump here
represents f.
All right?
So, how does So, the question then is
how does the action change when we
change X a little bit? All right, that's
easy to work out. Oh, incidentally,
yeah, let's write this out. The change
in X
is just equal to epsilon times f of t.
And of course, it also follows that the
change in the velocity
is epsilon times
f dot of t. We just differentiate with
respect to time both sides of the
equation.
If X changes by a little bit, then the
velocity associated with X changes a
little bit.
And we can imagine we have any number of
coordinates and do the same thing. It's
not restricted to just one coordinate,
but let's fix on X
and see what this equation says. All
right, so this is easy to work out. We
just write that this is that the change
in the action
is equal
to the change in the Lagrangian
integrated with respect to time. But
what's the change in the Lagrangian if
we change X and X dot a little bit?
Well, that's easy. That's the derivative
of the Lagrangian
with respect to X
times delta X, but delta X is just
proportional to f of t. We can put an
epsilon on the outside here.
The change of X
is just f of t.
So, let's put f of t there.
Epsilon times f of t, but I left the
epsilon outside. And then, the
Lagrangian also depends on the velocity.
So, we add plus the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to the velocity
times the change in the velocity.
Integral dt.
That's the change in the action
when we change the trajectory a little
bit by an amount
delta of X dot, sorry, is just epsilon f
dot.
f dot. Epsilon is already outside here.
Any question about this formula thus
far?
It's just a simple formula that the
change in the action is gotten by
varying the Lagrangian a little bit
by varying X and by varying X dot.
Now, what's the next step? Anybody
remember?
Integration by parts. This over here.
The f dot. And what we're using is that
if you have a
integral of the form of the product of
two functions a times b dot,
that's equal to minus
the integral of a dot times b
as long as you don't vary the end
points. As long as things are frozen at
the end points, then there's no
contribution from the boundary
in the integration by parts. And so,
it's very easy. Wherever you see a time
derivative, if you have a product in an
integral,
this of course is dt.
If you have a product in an integral of
something times a time derivative of
something else, you can switch which one
of them carries the time derivative, but
you have to change the sign.
All right, so that's the rule of
integration by parts.
And that's what we have over here. We
have a time derivative f dot over here
times dl by dx dot.
So, all we have to do then,
we can do, not all we have to do, but
what we can do is change the sign,
put the time derivative
on the other factor,
and get rid of the time derivative here.
Now, why was that a nice thing to do? It
was a nice thing to do because it
isolates f
by itself without a time derivative in
both terms.
So, that means we can factor out of the
bracket, not out of the integral, but
out of the square bracket here, we can
factor f. Both terms are proportional to
f.
And we have f dt, f of t dt.
Now, what do we want to be true?
We want this to be true that this is
equal to zero for every possible
variation f of t.
We want to explore all neighboring
trajectories, all possible neighboring
trajectories,
and require that every possible shift in
the trajectory, in other words, every
possible f
gives the same answer when you vary the
action to first order,
namely zero.
All right? So, that means that this has
to be zero for all functions f of t, all
possible functions. Well, if you think
about it a little while, you realize the
only way an integral like this can be
zero for all possible f of t is for the
thing that it multiplies to be zero.
Supposing the thing that it multiplied
here was not equal to zero somewheres,
for some at some time.
Supposing the thing that was here was
not equal to zero at some time,
then we could choose a function of time
that was
the f of t that was narrowly
concentrated
near the place where we knew the thing
in the brackets was not equal to zero,
concentrated only in that region, and we
would get something not equal to zero. f
not equal to zero, this thing not equal
to zero over a small enough range, we'll
get something not equal to zero. So, the
only way
that an integral like this can be zero
for every possible f of t is for the
integrand here to be zero, for the thing
in the bracket to be zero.
This is analogous to testing the
function in all possible directions.
All possible directions, all possible
variations,
if you require that f be stationary with
respect to all possible variations, it
tells you that all of the derivatives
equal to zero.
The analog here is that what's in here
in the bracket must be zero for all
possible for all times between here and
here.
That's the Euler-Lagrange equations.
That's the derivation of the
Euler-Lagrange equations.
Let's write them down.
d by dt
of the derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to
X dot
minus the derivative of Lagrangian with
respect to X. Let's use the same symbol
here.
All right. Now, the only difference
if we have lots of coordinates, now
let's call the coordinates Q instead of
X.
They might not be the Cartesian
coordinates of a particle. They might
include angles,
uh
points along some arbitrary curve, some
more generalized kind of coordinates.
Exactly the same thing will be true
except we'll just call the X's Q's.
We'll call the X's Q's.
It's just a renaming.
But if there are many many coordinates,
well, many or more than one,
then we'll want to put an i there.
And so, for each coordinate, X, Y, Z,
different particles, there will be a
Euler-Lagrange equation, which is
essentially of the form of Newton's
equations for each component of the
uh of the configuration space.
So, we've been through that. I assume
that uh you have that in your notes.
That's the derivation of Euler-Lagrange.
And it's the basic equation of
Lagrangian mechanics.
Uh
Now, we want to generalize that to field
theory.
Field theory is a special case of this
where the various coordinates correspond
to the values of fields at different
positions of space.
We worked out an example, which was the
string,
by dividing subdividing space into a lot
of little
segments, or a lot of little positions,
and then instead of thinking of a
continuous field, we thought of the
value of a field
at each point.
We discretized it. We discretize the
field and replaced it by a rather dense
collection of degrees of freedom.
We called the degrees of freedom. We
didn't call them X because X now labels
position labels
doesn't label a location of any of a
particle.
It labels a location in space.
In other words, it labels
the position that we might be evaluating
the field.
The field becomes the coordinate.
The field becomes the degree of freedom.
In other words, the Q's in this problem
are the fields at the different
positions. We could call it Q of i.
Sorry, phi of i.
Meaning phi at the position at the ith
position, or we could call it
phi at point xi,
or we can just call it phi of x.
Phi of x sort of has the implication
that we're going to a limit where we
take the points to be so dense
that this field becomes a continuous
field.
And we can imagine doing that process
and if we do imagine it,
then the field theory just is a special
case of classical mechanics where the
Q's are just the values of the fields at
the different points. Now, I emphasize
they are not locations of anything in
space,
they are the values of fields at
different points in space.
But, as we discussed last time,
you can summarize all of this passing
from a discrete description to a
continuous description, replacing sums
by integrals, differences by
derivatives.
We can summarize all of this
by saying we have a Lagrangian
which begins as a sum over position,
sum of all the kinetic energies, sum of
all the potential energies,
and
uh
becomes replaced by an integral
the X. Now, as I said, X now does not
stand Lagrangian is
an integral the X. The integral over X
replaces the sum
over I.
Integral the X of some Lagrange density.
Lagrange density means you integrated
over space to find the Lagrangian. What
does the Lagrange density depend on?
In general, the Lagrange density will
depend on
the values of the fields at each
position.
It will depend on phi of X.
It may also depend on differences of phi
at neighboring points. Yeah.
Is there some
meaning between searching for uppercase
lowercase L?
Oh, of of which the L?
Of which of which of phi? No, none
whatever. Have I switched?
Oh, you you consider this uppercase?
Yeah. Oh, no. Uppercase I will If I do
use uppercase, I will do this. Okay.
Yeah.
No, that's just uh sloppy uh
No, none whatever.
Good.
Right. So, phi of X Right. So, the sum
over degrees the sum over the degrees of
freedom becomes an integral over X of a
of a thing which is called the Lagrange
density.
And in general, the Lagrange density
will depend on phi.
It will depend on time derivatives of
phi,
just like Lagrangians depend on Q's and
Q dots.
Lagrangian will depend on phi. It will
depend on phi dot, which means the time
derivative with respect to time with
respect to T.
The derivative with respect to T. And
let me write that
just as
DT phi.
That's shorthand for D phi by DT.
Here's some here's some equiva-
uh notational equivalences.
Phi dot equals D phi by DT
equals DT phi
equals phi sub T.
All the same thing. Isn't
phi dot really
Hm? DDT?
D phi DT? Well, it's not the partial,
it's the total. No, no, it's the
partial.
That's what I mean by phi dot.
What if it were
omega dot? Wouldn't it be the total
derivative?
What's omega?
Angular momentum or I mean, you know, in
general Well, if a thing depends on more
than one variable, and phi depends on
more than one variable,
then it has a collection of derivatives
with respect to each variable.
But I'm just saying usually isn't the
dot always the total derivative? Uh
If you like if you want me to use phi
dot total derivative, no, I I don't use
it that way, and I don't think it's
commonly used that way. Um but let's
Okay, let's not
X dot equals a Poisson bracket or
something like that.
Yeah, let's not use Fine. I'll
I'll uh I'll
In fact,
modern physicists don't use it that way.
They use it quite often to mean
derivative with respect to T keeping
everything else fixed.
Yeah.
In fact, I
it's so easy to write it that I think I
want to keep it around as a notation.
That's definition now. Definition of phi
dot derivative with respect to T. And if
I ever have a situation where I want to
think about the total derivative of
something,
the total derivative may mean along some
orbit or something, then I would just
write D phi by DT. Capital I'll write D
phi DT.
Since I will so rarely have to use this,
uh I prefer to save uh more complicated
notation for um something I use rarely.
Okay. These are all the same thing,
and uh
I
Let's put
phi sub T here.
Meaning to say the derivative of phi
with respect to T keeping everything
else fixed. But what else can L depend
on?
L can also depend on differences of phi
between neighboring points.
All right. So, you could have in the
Lagrangian
phi appearing at each point separately,
but you could also have the derivatives
of phi
appearing in the expression for the
Lagrangian. And in the Lagrangian we
wrote down,
the uh potential energy did involve
differences of phi at two different
points.
That translated into something involving
derivatives of phi
with respect to
spatial positions.
All right.
So, we could have equals DX phi
equals phi X. We can also have D phi by
DY and so forth.
So,
what can appear here is derivatives of
phi with respect to T,
derivatives of phi with respect to X,
and derivatives of phi with respect to
Y, and derivatives of phi with respect
to Z.
All of them can appear in the
Lagrangian.
Notice it's kind of symmetric between
T's, X's, Y's, and Z's.
Uh I don't just call this derivatives of
phi with respect to the coordinates.
I can also call these derivatives
phi sub mu
where mu runs from zero to four,
T being X zero, X being X one, Y being X
two, and Z being X three in our sort of
relativistic notation.
All these things mean the same thing.
You want to change the DX and have
DX to what?
Where?
Yeah, I I was just about to change that.
Here. Yeah. Yeah, exactly. That's right.
But the integral DX, when I was thinking
about a string, there was only one space
coordinate.
When I'm thinking about a field in three
dimensions,
then I want to put D three X.
All right. Now, first of all,
what is kinetic energy and what is
potential energy? In the example we
worked out here, the
uh the Lagrangian had, for example, phi
dot squared in it.
That was simply the kinetic energy of
every point oscillating up and down.
When we thought about it as a string,
phi dot squared was the kinetic energy.
So, typically in a Lagrangian like this,
there will be a term 1/2
phi dot squared.
That's kinetic energy.
All right. It depends and kinetic energy
by definition
means the things which are quadratic in
the velocities.
And velocity mean derivative with
respect to time.
All right. So, a typical Lagrangian
might have
1/2
phi dot squared.
And then in the example we worked out
over there, there was a minus C squared.
Why was there a minus sign here? Anybody
remember?
In the potential energy?
Because the Lagrangian is kinetic energy
minus potential energy.
All right.
And what was the potential energy? The
potential energy depended on the
difference of the field at neighboring
positions.
And so there was D phi by DX
squared.
And of course, in a more general
context,
we might also have minus C squared
D phi by DY squared
minus C squared D phi by D
Z squared.
It's good to write it explicitly just to
keep track and to remember that this
term is kinetic energy, and this stuff
here is potential energy.
It doesn't depend on velocities. It
doesn't depend on the motion. It does
depend on the configuration, how the
phi's are ori- how they their dependence
on on space, but not on time.
So, this term here is the uh is the
kinetic energy.
This is potential energy. There could be
other terms in here.
There could be things which depend on
phi itself without derivatives.
It's a perfectly rational thing to put
into a uh Lagrangian. For example, each
one of these particles
could have an energy which depends on
its height.
Not on the difference between
neighboring heights, but there could be
a term in the energy which would just
depend on the height of each particle.
For example, if the whole thing was in a
gravitational field.
Okay?
Then we might put into here something
which depends on phi.
Not the phi by the x, not the phi by the
t, but possibly just phi itself.
So, there might also be dependence on
phi. Let's put some dependence on phi in
here.
A nice simple example would be minus
some constant. I'll call it mu and I'll
put a two there for
purely conventional reasons times phi
squared.
And I choose phi squared
for no specific reason except that it
makes an easy equation when we work out
the equation of motion. It could be phi
cubed, it could be phi by itself, it
could be cosine of phi.
But something which depends on phi and
not its derivatives. So, this would be a
term in the potential energy which would
depend on the coordinate of each one of
these separately, not on the differences
between them. Whereas the potential
energy could also have a dependence on
the
gradient of phi, the gradient in space.
All right, this is the Lagrange density
here. The Lagrangian is the integral of
that.
But the action, the action is the
integral of the Lagrangian with respect
to time. So, that's yet one more
integral.
The action
is the integral of this
dt, which means d4x.
That's the structure That's the general
structure of field theory. Not that
specific Lagrangian,
but a Lagrange density integrated over
space and time
uh
is the starting point
of most
discussions of field theory. We'll start
with the Lagrangian. Now, what is the
condition that the theory be Lorentz
invariant?
The condition that the theory be Lorentz
invariant is very, very simple.
You, of course, first must start with
some idea of what kind of transformation
properties your field variables have.
The field variables could be scalars,
they could be vectors, four vectors. We
have You have to give them a
transformation property under Lorentz
transformations,
not just under rotations of space.
So, the field variables could be
any any particular kind of as I said,
scalars, vectors,
tensors which we haven't spoken spoken
about yet.
But in this simple case, I'm imagining
the field variable as a scalar.
We'll go on to more complicated cases
with vectors, but for the moment, just
scalars. The field variable phi is a
scalar.
The important thing is that the Lagrange
density be a scalar.
If the Lagrange density is a scalar, it
means the action doesn't depend on which
Lorentz frame you use.
So, if the
Lagrange density script L here
is a scalar,
you don't have to even think about
whether the equations are Lorentz
invariant, they will be.
All right. Now, this is a Lorentz As
I've written it here, this is a Lorentz
scalar.
It has the form
phi dot squared minus c squared. Let's
set c equal to one for simplicity.
Uh
at least at this stage, let's set c
equal to one.
The thing in the Lagrangian is d mu phi
d mu phi.
Remember what this means.
This stands for the four derivatives,
time derivative and the three space
derivatives.
These things here.
These stand for the same derivatives
except with a change of sign of the time
component.
All right? So, d mu phi stands for the
complex of objects
phi t,
phi x,
up to phi z.
And d super mu phi stands for the same
thing except the time component's
changing.
Then when I multiply
the contravariant derivative times the
covariant derivative,
it gives me something with a time
derivative squared
having the opposite sign from the space
derivatives. In fact, I think I want to
put a minus sign in here, huh?
And a two.
So, the Lagrange density that I've
written down over here
is nothing but
the scalar which is made by contracting
together
the covariant
components of the gradient of phi with
the contravariant components.
That makes a scalar.
And as a scalar,
it tells us the action is invariant. And
if the action is invariant, the
equations of motion will be invariant.
So, it's real easy to design
relativistically invariant theories.
Does that include the c squared term?
What's that?
Does it include the last term? Oh, this
one here?
Well, in fact, it does. Since phi is a
scalar, so is phi squared.
that
that what you wrote down is
Oh, sorry. Yes, you're right.
Minus mu over two phi squared.
Is that mu over four or is it Is that
two squarely like outside?
Thank you.
Of course, it doesn't matter. It's
definition of mu, but I did intend that
that the mu also had a factor of two,
right?
All right.
Good. Okay.
So,
uh
That's the basic setup. Now, the next
question is, given a Lagrangian like
this,
what are the Euler-Lagrange What are the
analogs of the Euler-Lagrange equations?
In other words, what are the field
equations as partial differential
equations?
For the case of a
coordinate which only depends on one
variable, namely time,
the Euler-Lagrange equations were just
ordinary differential equations for the
time dependence.
Now, we have a problem which is to
figure out not only the dependence of
phi on time, but also on space and time.
And so, the equations are going to be
partial differential equations or wave
equations, wave equations to be
specific.
So, the question is, how do you take a
thing like this and minimize it?
Let's just take this to be a special
case.
Here's the general form.
L is equal to an integral d cubed x of
this kind of thing here. The action,
let's write the action
is the integral d4x.
Well, you do exactly the same thing as
in uh
as in the uh
in the simpler case.
You say, let's
suppose
that phi of x and t,
which I could just write as phi of x mu,
but phi of x and t, let's suppose that's
a solution.
And now let's add plus epsilon
times a function of x and t to it.
What we require is that when we change
the field in this manner,
that the change in the action
is equal to zero.
That's the analog of saying that the
action is stationary. In fact, it's not
the analog, it's a statement that the
action is stationary when you change the
uh the orbit of the field. Think of this
is sort of the orbit,
how the field varies in space and time
is the generalization of the orbit of a
mechanical system.
And we're requiring that the
action be stationary.
Well, let's work it out. This is not so
hard to do.
Um
if
delta phi
is equal to epsilon times f of x and t,
then what is the change in, let's call
it
phi mu?
What's the change if the If there's a
change in phi, what is the change in the
derivative of phi with respect to x?
Very simple. It's just equal to epsilon
times the derivative of f with respect
to x mu.
So, for example, this stands for the
complex of equations
I don't have to write them now,
that the change in the time derivative
of phi is epsilon times the time
derivative of f.
And likewise for the other components, f
of x and t.
If you change phi by a little bit,
then the change in the derivatives is
just the derivatives of the change in
phi.
Okay, so now let's calculate the change
in the action.
The change in the action
is going to be the integral d4x
times the change in the Lagrangian when
I change the the field a little bit.
And what is that? That's the derivative
of the Lagrangian density
with respect to phi
times delta phi.
That's epsilon epsilon on the outside
f of x and t.
Plus
the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to phi mu
phi mu
phi mu, phi t, phi x, phi y, phi z
times
the change in phi mu, which is the f
by the x mu.
I think I have that right.
And of course this stands for a sum.
This stands for a sum over x, y, and z.
Or x, y, z, and t, all of them.
That's it. That's the change in the
action.
What do I want to do? I want to set this
equal to zero.
That's the condition that the action be
stationary.
Now, over here I have f of x and t. Here
I have the derivatives of f. What do I
do to go from uh to to to get rid of
this derivative on f here?
Integrate parts.
The rule for integrating by parts, I'm
not going to work it out for you but the
rule for multiple multiple dimensional
integrals is exactly the same as the
rule
for single integrals.
You're allowed to take the derivative
off here and put it on here
at the expense of a a sign change.
So this is the same thing as
minus
and now the derivative with respect to x
goes here.
Let me write it out.
Let me write it out uh
a little more clearly.
Minus d by dx mu
of the derivative of the Lagrange
density
with respect to phi mu
times f of x and t again.
All right. Now we're getting close to
being in business.
We have f multiplying both factors here.
So I can put a bracket around here
and factor out the f.
The next step is exactly as the same as
it was in the particle case.
This is supposed to be equal to zero
for all possible functions of x. For all
possible ways of changing the field away
from the solution
in other words, you're exploring all
variations of the field away from the
solution and requiring that the action
is stationary
this has to be zero for all f.
How is that possible? It is only
possible if the thing in the bracket
here is zero.
So
we come to the conclusion that for each
field in the problem, we're dealing now
with a problem with only one field, phi.
If there were several fields, you would
have a separate equation for each one
but let's deal with the case of one
field. Our equation of motion
our Euler-Lagrange equation of motion
which follows from the Lagrangian is
here it is.
Take the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to phi mu
differentiate it with respect to x mu.
This is in close analogy with the
derivative of the ordinary Lagrangian
with respect to q dot
d by dt.
All right. Close analogy but there are
four terms in here. Derivative of the
respect to t
with respect to x, with respect to y,
with respect to z and then subtract off
minus the
the derivative with
of l with respect to phi
equals zero.
All right. So now we have a kind of
machine. You feed into it a Lagrange a
scalar Lagrange density
and I think from now on I'm simply going
to call l script l the Lagrangian.
Uh
it's properly called the Lagrange
density but uh it's a mouthful.
For a field theory, we'll just call it
the Lagrangian.
Uh maybe I won't. Maybe I'll continue to
call it the Lagrange density but if I
slip and call it the Lagrangian
either correct me or um
well, it doesn't
if it's clear, don't bother.
All right. So this is our equation of
motion and now let's work it out. This
is our equation of motion for a field
phi. Let's work it out for our favorite
Lagrangian over here. Here's a specific
Lagrangian.
Let's work it out.
This here
is a sum.
Okay? So let's start. What does it say?
It says
The only thing we have to remember is
that the time components get the
opposite sign from the space components.
That's the main thing here.
All right. So this says the d by dt
of partial of l with respect to phi dot
that's the first term.
I guess minus
d by dx
partial of l
with respect to phi x and likewise for y
and z.
Minus the derivative with respect to phi
equals zero. And let's work it out now.
What's the derivative of this Lagrangian
with respect to phi dot?
Just phi dot.
One half gets eaten up by the two here.
The derivative of this thing inside the
bracket with respect to phi dot is just
phi dot.
Okay? So our first term here becomes
the l by d phi dot is just replaced by
phi dot.
And what's d by dt of phi dot?
Phi double dot.
Two time derivatives. Second time
derivative with respect to t or just phi
tt. We could call it phi tt.
Second time derivative of phi with
respect to t.
Now, what about the derivative of the
Lagrangian
I made a mistake. This should be a This
is a plus sign here.
The minus The minus is here.
No, there's no minus over here. There
There's This should not be minus. This
is plus.
All right. What's partial of l with
respect to phi x?
It's minus c squared times phi x.
All right. So let's put that one in.
Minus
c squared
phi x
What's the derivative of phi x with
respect to x?
Phi xx.
Two derivatives.
I'll write it out in longhand in a
moment but let's uh
And likewise for y and z.
So there's minus c squared
phi yy
minus c squared phi zz.
And now let's include this last term
just for fun. I'm going to drop it soon
because uh it'll come back but
for most of tonight I'll get rid of
this. Minus mu phi squared. So we have
to uh subtract the derivative of
Where is our equation? We have to
subtract
minus the the
derivative of l with respect to phi
and I think that gives us I think a plus
mu phi mu phi.
Plus two.
Mhm.
Right?
Equals zero.
I guess equal zero. Is equal to zero.
Zero.
No, there isn't a half.
Because each one of these things was
squared. So when you differentiate it,
that's why the half is there. The half
is there to avoid the half in the
equation of motion.
Right?
That's uh All right. So let me write
this out in longhand.
In longhand, it's second derivative of
phi with respect to t squared
minus c squared
second of phi with respect to x squared
plus second of phi with respect to y
squared
plus second of phi with respect to z
all equals Sorry.
Let's put the plus mu phi
plus mu phi
equals zero.
Okay.
I only kept the mu phi there
just to illustrate in some generality
what it would mean to have a term
Lagrangian or a piece of Lagrangian
which depends explicitly on phi.
I'm going to drop it now. We're going to
come back to it.
Mhm?
Is it a minus sign? I think it's a plus
sign.
Or it's two minus. I think it's a plus
sign, yeah.
Right.
Okay. Incidentally, the mu phi squared
term is called the mass term and it has
a great deal to do with the mass of the
quanta
of the field. In fact, it is nothing but
the square of the mass
of a particle uh that might be described
by this field.
Remember, there's a connection between
fields and particles through quantum
mechanics.
So the electromagnetic field, the
particles that it describes are photons.
Uh
photons have no mass.
So, you would not have this term for
photons.
Other particles which have mass, you
would have this term. But, let's uh
we're going to come to that. Well, why
do I say it's a mass? Well, it's not in
the least bit obvious at the moment.
But, let's just drop it and study the
theory without that term. Here is the
equation describing um
uh it describes light.
It describes the propagation of any
massless field.
Sorry, it describes any field which
propagates with the speed of light.
Let's uh let's just look at it in one
dimension.
We've of course already done this.
For example, supposing the field only
depends on time, of course it depends on
time. If it's any kind of decent field,
it's going to depend on time.
But, supposing it doesn't depend on all
three coordinates. Suppose it only
depends on X and not Y and Z.
How can that be? Well, if a wave was
moving down the X axis,
a plane wave with no variation
perfectly uniform wave fronts
moving down the X axis, then it would
have no dependence on the other two
directions.
A uniform infinite plane wave moving
down the axis like this would have no
dependence on Y and Z.
And so, for that situation, the wave
equation would be
the second phi by dt squared
minus c squared the second phi by dx
squared
is equal to zero.
All right.
There are in fact
two kinds of solutions of this equation.
This is the standard wave equation of a
field which propagates with a uniform
velocity c.
And the solutions of these equations are
functions
two kinds, two of them. Any function
of x minus ct
or a function of
x plus ct.
Doesn't have to be the same function.
Take any function, let's call it f.
Let's not call it phi. Let's write
phi
is equal to any function of x minus ct.
In fact, you can add plus another
function
of x plus ct.
What does this term describe?
Right.
You start at t equals zero with some any
old function of x.
And now, when you write function of x
minus ct, it just describes exactly that
same profile moving with velocity c down
the x axis.
What about this one?
That just describes the profile g moving
in the opposite direction, in the left
direction.
Now, of course, there was nothing sacred
about a wave moving along the x axis. I
could have rotated it and have it moved
along any axis or even any uh
you know, cater-cornered axis.
But,
this is the uh the typical kind of
solutions of these wave equations.
The wave shape is maintained.
That's right. That would not be the case
if we added in
the mu
Was it plus or minus? I think it was
minus. Plus or minus
mu phi.
In other words, with this extra term
over here, it would not be the case
then.
So, this is a special feature of uh
of uh
what is called the massless wave
equation.
It's called the massless wave equation.
It corresponds to the fact that
this this describes waves that move with
a particular fixed velocity.
Uh so, the whole thing just moves off
with a uniform velocity.
Same way a light ray would.
Uh light beam would. Yeah, question.
But, but if g of x is not the
If g If what? If you have the two of
them, then they
the the this
they're different shapes moving.
So, it doesn't look like a wave. Oh,
yeah, yeah, yeah. No. Right.
Yeah, you could have Sure. You could
have a shape like this moving to the
right and add on to it a shape which
looks like
this
moving to the left.
And of course, when they pass through
each other,
you're going to see something much more
complicated. But, all they're really
doing is passing through each other
without uh doing anything very
interesting.
All right. So, that's the uh general
pattern.
Left moving waves and right moving
waves.
Uh
phi is not a sufficient initial
condition. What's the Say it again? Phi
itself is not a sufficient initial
condition. That's right. What's the
other part of the initial
Time derivative of phi.
Yeah.
Um For example, here's the point.
This
Another way to say it is this. Supposing
I just gave you the field phi at time
zero.
Here it would be f of x plus g of x.
How do I know that some piece of it is
right moving? How do I know how to
divide this up into This is just The sum
of these two is just some function.
How do I know how to divide it up into
left moving parts and right moving
parts?
Well, if I also tell you what the time
derivative is,
then knowing both the function and the
time derivative allows you to break it
up into into the two parts like that.
That's a little exercise you can do.
So, yes, you need to know phi and phi
dot.
Same exact story as with
uh with uh particles
or with ordinary coordinates, you need
to know the coordinates and the time
derivatives to get started.
All right.
In any case, for the simple wave
equation without mass term,
uh
this is what you get. Now,
notice this equation, either with or
without the mass term, the equation is
linear.
Linear means only first powers of phi
appear.
Higher derivatives of phi appear, but
nothing ever involving products of phi
or derivatives of phi times phi or
derivatives of phi with other
derivatives of phi.
Linear equation means that the only
thing that appears in it are first
powers of phi, derivative of phi, second
derivative of phi, and so forth.
Under those circumstances, you can add
solutions. If you have two solutions of
the equation,
you can add them together and they're
still a solution.
You can also multiply the solutions by a
number and it's still a solution.
So, a linear equation, you can add
solutions. Here, I've just done it.
You can multiply solutions by numbers.
And they're still solutions.
This equation is linear even with the
mass term.
What is it from the point of view of the
Lagrangian that made the equation
linear?
The Lagrangian is quadratic.
It involves phi squared, derivatives of
phi squared,
uh squares of derivatives of phi Sorry,
squares of derivatives of phi, and so
forth.
So, it only involves things to the
second power.
That means when you differentiate the
Lagrangian
with respect to its various arguments,
you'll only get first powers of phi.
And so, if the Lagrangian is quadratic,
the equation of motion is linear.
Do you know a mechanics problem that has
a linear equation of motion?
Mechanics meaning to say not field
theory, but just particle motion.
Harmonic oscillator.
Yeah.
Well, first even simpler would just be a
free particle.
x dot squared.
Okay.
That's equation of motion is just x
double dot equals zero, and that's very
linear.
Well, you can't be very linear. You're
either linear or you're not linear.
Uh
But, if you want to have a more
interesting example involving some
potential energy, then for the potential
energy in Lagrangian minus
uh some constant times x squared.
So, it's the quadratic character of the
Lagrangian, which in turn means the
quadratic character of the potential and
kinetic energy,
which make the equation linear. Just to
remind you, the equation of a harmonic
oscillator is x double dot equals minus
kx.
Again, only first powers.
And linear equations are particularly
simple to to study.
Okay, that's uh that's
The
mass part
attenuates the wave always. Does it
what? The mass part attenuates the wave.
No, it doesn't attenuate the wave. What
it does is it causes All right, I'll
tell you what it does.
It causes different wavelengths. You can
think of any wave as being made up of
different wavelengths. All right. It
causes different wavelengths to
propagate with different velocities.
Dispersion. The result is it causes the
shape of the wave to change. So, the
shape of the wave changes with time. It
doesn't disperse away. It doesn't It
doesn't fade away, but it does cause the
shape to change and it'll wobble and do
things and more complicated kind of
motion.
All right.
We'll solve We'll We'll solve these
equations.
But, what I wanted to do tonight really
was not to solve equations of motion,
but to study conservation laws. An awful
lot of field theory, quantum field
theory, elementary particle physics,
uh the whole works is the study of
symmetries
and the and the associated conservation
laws. So, let's take a 5-minute break
and then come back and immerse ourselves
in the theory of symmetries and the
associated conservation laws.
Two cases of the connection of the
connections between Now,
they're really not two cases, but I just
wanted to for simplicity uh separate
them uh
now.
One of them has to do with energy
conservation and the other all other
conservation laws.
Energy conservation is a little bit
special,
although it can be cast in the same form
as the others. What symmetry does it
have to do with?
Excuse me.
Translation of the action with respect
to time. In other words, if there's no
special origin of time in your problem,
for example, how could you have a
a not a problem in which there was not
time translation invariance
incidentally?
Yeah, for example, universe is
expanding. Uh
one time is not like another time.
So, that would be an example. Some
problem with some bizarre uh reason the
force law was changing with time.
Uh
so, you can certainly imagine problems
where you don't have time translation
invariance,
but most problems in physics have time
translation invariance, which means it
doesn't matter at what time you start.
If you start the same way at one time or
another time, the ensuing histories will
be the same except just lagging one
behind the other by the uh by the time
shift.
When that happens, you have energy
conservation and I'm not going to go
back through the derivation of that.
That we did in the mechanics class
and it's a little more intricate than
the other ones. So, I'll I'll just ask
you to go back and
and recall
the argument about how time translation
invariance leads to energy conservation.
But, the energy conservation statement
itself is very simple.
If the Lagrangian,
let's simplify the story to simple
Lagrangians. We may get the more
complicated ones at some point. But, if
the Lagrangian can be separated into
kinetic and potential terms.
Now, kinetic terms mean terms which are
quadratic in velocities.
Velocities mean time derivatives. Not
space derivatives, but time derivatives.
If the Lagrangian has a term
which is a time derivative squared or a
time derivative of one thing times a
time derivative of another thing.
In other words, it's quadratic in time
derivatives, then those terms are called
kinetic.
All right.
So, for example, in our example,
the term 1/2 phi dot squared
is called kinetic
kinetic field energy.
Kinetic energy of the field. It's not
kinetic energy in the sense of something
moving down uh the down the corridor
here. It's kinetic energy in the sense
that the field is moving with respect to
time. Field is changing with respect to
time. So, this is kinetic.
T, let's call it T for
or just K, kinetic energy
would be that. Things which do not
depend at all on time derivatives
are potential energy.
All right. So, what are the potential
energy? We call it U.
That will have 1/2 in our example over
there.
Uh 1/2
the
space derivatives
plus 1/2.
So, these constitute potential energy.
If you think about it for a minute, when
we worked out the problem of the chain
of springs,
the space derivative terms came from the
stretching of springs. The time
derivative terms actually came from
kinetic energy of the motion of the mass
points connecting the springs. So, in
fact, these space derivatives really do
correspond to something more like
potential energy than kinetic energy,
but they potential energy which depend
on neighboring points
on the field configuration and
neighboring points, but they don't
depend on velocities, only on gradients.
We could call these grade as spatial
gradients.
All right. What else did we have in the
potential energy? In the potential
energy,
we also could We also could have this mu
phi squared term.
So, I think it was plus
mu
phi squared over two.
Then, kinetic energy minus potential
energy is the Lagrangian density. All
Actually, is this the kinetic energy?
Not strictly speaking, the kinetic
energy is the integral of this over
space.
It's the sum of all the kinetic energies
of all the fields at all the positions
in space.
In the case of a string, the full
kinetic energy is the sum of the kinetic
energies of all the moving mass points.
So, strictly speaking, the kinetic
energy is the integral of this.
Let me put it in in blue here. It's
really the integral d3x.
And the potential energy would be the
integral
also.
But, sometimes we lapse into a simpler
language and just call this term the
kinetic energy without the integral and
this term the potential energy.
Okay.
And of course, we can have more
complicated expressions. This is not
This does not exhaust all possibilities.
In fact, there's no reason why you can't
put here phi to the fourth or phi to the
10th power or whatever you like,
but
as long as it doesn't have time
derivatives, it's part of the potential
energy.
Now, the Lagrangian is the difference of
the two kinds of energy.
Let me put my
Yeah, I lost it.
Um Lagrangian is the difference, but the
energy itself,
which in Hamiltonian mechanics becomes
the Hamiltonian of course, but let's not
worry about that. The full energy
is kinetic energy
plus potential energy.
So, it's the sum of these.
Phi dot squared plus the gradient of phi
squared plus mu phi squared. Notice that
in the energy in this form, all of the
terms are positive.
All the terms are positive, kinetic
energy, potential energy, and even the
term coming from the mu phi squared
are all positive.
Of course, nothing to prevent me from
putting this in in with a negative sign,
but I didn't on purpose.
So, the energy typically has
some kind of positivity associated with
it.
What if phi is absolutely zero? In other
words, no field, no waves at all.
Then, the energy is zero.
Phi is zero, the derivative of phi is
zero, and so forth. The energy is
completely zero.
Also, mu phi squared is zero.
And since the expression for the energy
is positive, if phi is not zero, the
energy of anything which is not just phi
equals zero is positive. So, any wave or
any configuration of the field is
positive. Has a positive energy, unless
the field is just plain zero.
Plain zero is called the vacuum
and anything with a varying phi or a
non-zero phi
carries energy and is called an excited
state.
Okay. So, that's uh that's energetics.
And if you go back to the original
formulation of mechanics in the in the
quarter on mechanics,
you'll discover that there's a
derivation of the fact that kinetic
energy plus potential energy is
conserved
if
the problem is time translation
invariant. So, this is our first
conservation law, conservation of
energy.
Uh later on, if we explore more
complicated Lagrangians, I'll remind you
of a more general definition of the
energy, but as long as the energy breaks
up into a kinetic term
quadratic in time derivatives and a
potential energy term, then kinetic plus
potential is conserved. That's a general
theorem.
We could prove it, but I I didn't want
to spend a lot of time at it since it
really just follows exactly the pattern
uh
It's not that I
didn't want to do it. It just take It's
a little too intricate uh to go over
again. Go back to your notes and uh
and uh
And as I said, it's a special case of
mechanics. So, you don't have to do it
over again for field theory. It's just a
special case of mechanics energy
conservation.
Now, there are other conservation laws.
The other conservation laws follow from
principles like this. Let me remind you
in ordinary mechanics.
Supposing you have a Lagrangian
No, an ordinary Lagrangian
which depends on some Q's and some Q
dots. Not just one, but a whole family
of them.
Now, supposing the Lagrangian is
unchanged
if you make certain
transformations on Q. If you If you do
something to Q and in particular, if you
take each Q sub I
and add to it a small change
which has the form F sub I of all the
Q's.
This means some the some Ith function of
all the Q's including Q sub I, Q1
through QN.
Supposing if I make such a change
supposing it's true that the Lagrangian
does just doesn't change.
That's called a symmetry. Let me give
you an example or a couple of examples.
Kinetic energy
of a free particle X dot squared
over two.
MX dot squared over two. Forget the
integral.
That's the Lagrangian.
Is there a transformation that I can do
that won't change the Lagrangian?
Yes.
Just take X
and add a small displacement to it.
This just corresponds to displacing your
system a little bit.
If you change X by a constant amount.
Incidentally, these Q's here these F's
are not supposed to depend on time. No
time dependence at all.
Just a constant shift of some kind of
the Q's.
Here's a constant shift of the X's. It
just corresponds to displacing your
system a little bit.
If I shift X by a constant amount, it
does not change X dot.
It doesn't change the velocity.
The change in the velocity zero
because epsilon doesn't depend on time.
So, the Lagrangian doesn't change if you
shift X a little bit.
That's one example.
Supposing I had added something.
Supposing I had added
Let's make it a harmonic oscillator KX
squared over two.
Now, what happens if I shift X a little
bit?
This term doesn't change, but this term
does change.
This is just a statement that if I have
a harmonic oscillator and I shift the
coordinate a little bit, the potential
energy changes.
So, the free particle
has a symmetry
shift of X.
The harmonic oscillator does not share
that symmetry, but now let's take
another problem. Let's take a problem
with two particles connected by a
spring.
Let's call the position of the first one
X and the position of the second one Y.
They don't correspond to two different
axes. They just correspond to two
particles X and Y.
All right. What's the energy? Kinetic
energy of the first particle is MX dot
squared over two.
Second particle, let's call it capital M
Y dot squared over two.
Now, what about the potential energy?
The potential energy only depends on the
distance between X and Y.
All right. It depends on how much the
string is the spring is stretched.
And so, the potential energy which goes
into the Lagrangian with a minus sign,
of course
that's going to have a spring constant K
over two
and it's going to have X minus Y
squared.
Okay.
Now, I assert that there's a symmetry.
The symmetry is to add to X and Y each
of them the same amount.
X goes to X plus epsilon and Y goes to Y
plus epsilon.
That's simply a shift of the whole
thing.
Both particles shifted by the same
amount.
What happens to the terms in the
Lagrangian? First of all, what happens
to X dot?
X dot doesn't change.
If you shift X by a constant amount, X
dot doesn't change. No change in X dot.
No change in the kinetic energy.
Likewise for the Y kinetic energy.
X changes
and Y changes, but X minus Y does not
change. You've shifted X and Y by
exactly the same amount. So, the
separation between X and Y has not
changed.
Potential energy has not changed. Again,
we have a symmetry.
It's the symmetry in this case of both
particles being shifted.
All right. So, let's think of some other
symmetries.
Supposing I have some system of
particles
interacting with various kinds of forces
and so forth.
Uh
As I illustrated here, one symmetry is
to shift the position of everything.
Shift in the X direction, shift in the Y
direction, shift in the Z direction.
As long as the forces
are as long as the potential energy only
depends on differences, then again, this
will be a symmetry. But we also have
other symmetries. Rotational symmetry.
Supposing I rotate the coordinates.
That's more complicated.
In that case
more complicated formulas for rotating
the coordinates, but nevertheless
uh as long as the forces only depend on
distances between particles
if you rotate a system, the energy
doesn't change, neither the kinetic
energy nor the potential energy. So
again, another symmetry of the problem.
Symmetries correspond
to changes that you can make in the
coordinates
time independent changes that don't
change the Lagrangian. That the
Lagrangian doesn't vary when you make
such a change. The value the numerical
value of the Lagrangian.
Whenever you have a symmetry like that
you also have a conservation law.
Let's prove that. It just follows very
simply from uh
from Lagrange's equations.
But we need a definition.
Well, we don't need a definition, but we
can use a definition.
The definition of the canonical momentum
conjugate to a coordinate Q.
All right. These are the Q's and the
P's. For every Q I
there is also a conjugate momentum P I.
Now, conjugate momenta may not look at
all like what you're ordinarily
accustomed to thinking of as momentum.
It's a mathematical definition of
something which for certain situations
looks like ordinary momentum.
It may or may not look and be familiar
you know, have a familiar connection
with mass times velocity.
Angular momentum for example is a thing
which doesn't look all that much like
ordinary velocity. And there are lots
and lots of other examples which look
even less like ordinary velocities of
things.
But, what is the definition of P sub I?
P sub I
is by definition the derivative of the
Lagrangian.
With respect to Q sub I dot.
It's the thing in the left hand side
of Lagrange's equation.
Lagrange's equation or the
Euler-Lagrange equation can also be
written in another form. They can be
written in the form d by dt
of P sub I, the time derivative of the
Ith
canonical momentum
is equal to the derivative of Lagrangian
with respect to Q sub I.
For each I.
All right. Everybody uh This is review.
I'm taking this to be review that a
canonical momentum is dL by dQ sub I
dot. Incidentally, what is the canonical
momentum
conjugate to X?
It's the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to X dot.
That's just MX dot.
MV.
So, for this kind of Lagrangian, it is
just your old familiar momentum.
Okay?
But more complicated situations, it may
be something else.
So, this is its mathematical definition
d by dt. Sorry.
P sub I
is the thing inside the square here.
Okay.
Let's prove a theorem.
Let's prove a theorem that if there is a
symmetry, in other words, if when you do
this operation
when you take each Q and shift it by an
amount F sub I
assume the Lagrangian doesn't change. In
other words, assume
that delta L
is equal to zero.
Under such a transformation, under such
a shift of the coordinates.
All right, then I assert that there is a
symmetry associated Sorry, it is a
symmetry. Then I assert that there's a
conservation law.
It's very easy to work out.
Let's see why that's so.
Here's Lagrange's equations of motion.
Let's multiply it by delta Q.
Well,
yeah.
Let's take each one of these equations
and multiply left-hand side and
right-hand side by the change in Q when
you do the little symmetry operation
here.
All right.
Good.
I can either write delta Q or I can
write epsilon
times F sub I of Q.
This whole thing being delta Q.
Delta Q sub I.
Let's do it also here. You're not
allowed to do something just on one
side, we have to do it on both sides.
F sub I of Q.
Now,
yeah, now let's sum.
Now let's sum over all the I's.
What's the left-hand side? The left-hand
side is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to Q times delta Q.
That's the amount the Lagrangian changes
when you do this operation.
But the assumption is that we have a
symmetry.
If we have If we have a symmetry,
then the right-hand side is by
definition zero. The change in the
Lagrangian when we shift Q times the
amount we change Q
under the symmetry operation.
That's assumed to be zero.
You don't prove that it's zero. You For
a specific Lagrangian, you prove that
it's zero.
But
for a specific Lagrangian, let's suppose
that the Lagrangian is invariant under
that operation, then this side must be
zero.
Definition of a symmetry.
On the other hand, the right-hand side
here, these F's are supposed to be not
time-dependent.
These are constant time-independent
shifts.
Not a shift which depends on a time, but
a shift which is completely independent
of time.
Then the time derivative of F is zero,
and we can write that this is the sum of
I
d by dt
of P sub I F sub I of Q.
In other words, you take the Ith
canonical momenta
and multiply it by the amount that you
shift the Ith Q. Ith Q.
By this.
That's equal to zero.
That's what this says.
Well, this is fantastic. That says we
have a conservation law. The
conservation law is the conservation
of P sub I F sub I of Q.
You take each shift, you take the shift
of the Ith coordinate F sub I. I think I
dropped epsilon out of this somewheres,
but epsilon multiplied both sides.
Yeah.
It just went along with F.
All right.
Uh we can drop it. If something is equal
to zero, it's equal to zero with or
without the epsilon multiplying it.
This quantity is conserved. Is
conserved.
Let's work out an example or two.
Well, here's an example right here.
Let's
First of all, delta X is equal to
epsilon.
Delta Y is equal to epsilon.
That's the common shift of both
coordinates.
All right.
Well, that says that F X
That just says that F X is equal to one
and F Y is equal to one.
X just shifts by amount epsilon. The
F is zero is one.
All right. What about the canonical
momentum? The canonical momentum
conjugate to X,
that's M X dot.
The canonical momentum conjugate to Y,
that's
P Y
is capital M Y dot.
What's the conserved quantity?
The conserved quantity is the sum
of P
times
the shift of each of the coordinates.
The shift of each of the coordinates is
just by one unit. I mean, you can drop
the epsilon. The epsilon is just there
to remind you that we're talking about a
small uh shift.
All right. So, what's the conserved
quantity? It's just P X plus P Y.
The total ordinary linear momentum.
But it's only conserved because the
potential energy
doesn't change when you make a shift.
Yeah.
So,
P X and P Y aren't
independently conserved? No, they're
not.
I've No, certainly not. Just think about
the motion of this two-particle system
with a spring. The two particles are
going like this.
The X component of this momentum is not
conserved. This
Yeah.
It's the center It's basically the
center of mass momentum which is
conserved.
Okay.
If there was no spring, the two would be
independently conserved.
All right. Because of the spring, only
one combination is conserved, and you
find that combination by finding the
symmetry.
Okay.
All right, let's apply this idea to
quan- to
to classical field theory.
Let's write down our Lagrangian and
search for various symmetries.
Uh
Do you have a question? Yeah. Uh was
that Noether's Noether's theorem? That's
the That's a simple case of Noether's
theorem. Yeah.
Yeah, that's exactly what it is.
Noether's theorem is a little more
general, but uh but uh this is uh simple
case of it.
All right, the first thing we have to do
is we have to understand what we mean by
coordinates and momenta, the conjugate
momenta to the coordinates. In a field
theory, the fields are the coordinates.
They're not the coordinates X, Y, and Z.
They're the mechanical They're the
analogs of mechanical degrees of
freedom, the Q's.
So, the coordinates
are
the fields.
And they're indexed by X instead of
being indexed by I.
What corresponds to the canonical
momentum? The canonical momentum
over here is the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to Q sub I dot.
Well,
and we call that
P, sometimes pi. I think I prefer to
call it pi now.
Pi sub I is equal to this.
Uh the reason I'm using pi is for
whatever reason
uh it is a conventional in field theory
to call the canonical momenta pi's. I
can't help the fact that the that uh
there are changes of convention as we go
along. These were established long ago.
But P and pi, same symbol. This is just
a Greek P.
So,
the canonical momentum
d L by d Q dot, what does that become?
It becomes the derivative of the
Lagrange density
with respect to phi dot.
It's that thing that was somewheres in
our Well, let's see. Where is our
Euler-Lagrange equation?
Here it is.
Well, one of these terms is d by dt of
partial of L with respect to phi dot.
All right.
Partial of L with res- with respect to
phi dot is the canonical momentum
conjugate to phi.
It's usually called pi sub phi.
And there's There's one at each point of
space. At each point of space,
there's a field phi, and at each point
of space, there's the canonical
conjugate to that, the canonical
momentum conjugate to that field. So,
both sides are functions of position.
What do we do?
Instead of summing over I when we want
to write some expression
uh that would that in mechanics would be
a sum over the coordinates,
we integrate over X. We integrate over
X. So, phi is a function of X. Pi is a
function of X.
And
otherwise, beyond that, it's just
straight mechanics.
All right.
Let's see if we can find some symmetries
and conserved quantities associated with
our simple field theories.
We had some
Let's take the simplest uh field theory
that we've written down.
Woo, I'm getting tired.
Um
I have a feeling I'm probably uh
reaching uh your point of exhaustion as
well as my own.
Yeah?
Yeah, I know.
Um
I think I think today's lecture was
fairly heavy-duty. Like uh
I'm not sure whether you've uh reached
saturation.
Somebody speak.
Yes.
Hm?
All right, I will go on a little bit,
but I will review it next time so you
can tune out now if you like, and I'll
try to uh
um
yeah.
All right, let's take our favorite
Lagrangians.
Simple one.
phi dot squared minus derivative of phi
with respect to x squared. And we could
put y squared and z squared there, too,
but just leave it like this for the
moment. Simple.
I've set the speed of light equal to 1.
Doesn't matter. Let's put the speed of
light in.
Can anybody spot a symmetry of this
Lagrangian?
Strictly speaking, the Lagrangian is the
integral dx of this.
dx 4, I guess,
Well, three d3x, but uh this is the
simple case for one-dimensional uh
one-dimensional string.
Uh but this is with
I just don't feel like writing the the
remaining terms, so
let's take this case, but there's no
difference in the uh
Can you spot a Can you spot any
symmetry?
Translation of what?
Which?
There's translation of the x axis,
indeed, but that's uh that Yes, we're
going to do that one.
There's a little simpler one.
It's translation of phi.
Supposing I take phi
of x and everywheres shift it by the
same amount.
phi of x plus epsilon.
This is a uniform shift of phi
everywheres.
Why is this a symmetry? Well, supposing
I shift phi, what happens to phi dot?
Nothing.
Because I'm assuming that epsilon here
was constant.
What happens to d phi by dx?
Epsilon is a constant, remember? It's
just a number.
Nothing happens.
So, this Lagrangian doesn't change
when you shift phi.
That means that there must be a
conserved quantity. What is that
conserved quantity?
It is
Let's
the sum over all Let's write the general
formula and then make it specific. It's
the sum over all the degrees of freedom
of
the canonical momentum
times Let's just uh let's times f uh
f sub i of q. But what is f sub i in
this case?
It's just one, right?
Everybody's been shifted by the same
amount.
So, the corresponding f that would
multiply here is just is just one. f
equals one everywheres. Everybody's been
shifted by the same amount.
And so, the answer for the conserved
quantity is the integral sum becomes
integral
dx
the canonical momentum conjugate to phi
times f, which is just one.
So, it's just the integral
of pi sub phi. But what is pi sub phi?
It's the derivative of Lagrangian with
respect to phi dot.
So, we've discovered a conservation law.
The integral dx
of phi dot of x
is conserved.
Now,
what does that say? Well, it says what
it says.
That uh for example, if uh
if you started the string, let's think
of it as a string, and we start the
string at time t equals zero with some
arbitrary shape
and some arbitrary velocity
moving in some way so that at every
point on the axis there is a phi dot,
then the integral of phi dot won't
change with time. What'll happen? This
phi dot, which is going up over here,
might get pulled back down. We know the
string wiggles.
So, this upward phi dot
might get pulled back down, but at the
same time this downward phi dot will get
pulled back up, and the net integrated
value of phi dot
would not change with time. That's what
we've proved.
Okay, so that's a conservation law.
Incidentally, it doesn't mean that the
integral of phi dot is zero. It means
the integral of phi dot doesn't change.
For example, we could start out
with a string
absolutely
stretched straight,
but with some part of it between here
and here
moving upward,
and every place else stationary.
The integral of phi dot is positive.
Why? Because phi dot is positive
everywheres. It's not zero.
And what will happen? With time, the
integral the the field will will move in
various ways, but the integral of the
velocity of the field will stay the
same. So, that's a conservation law.
Yeah. But if you have but but if if the
initial velocity is is zero, and but the
string is
stretched from its neutral position,
Right.
what happens then? It looks like uh the
the uh it's starting at zero velocity.
Yeah.
The integral Oh, oh, I know what you're
worried about. You're worried about what
happens if the string is uh is pinned
down at its ends.
At its ends. Yeah. Okay. That the
pinning down of the string breaks the
symmetry. Okay. It breaks the symmetry.
One way of thinking about the pinning
down of the ends is to imagine that
there's a huge force which is confining
the ends of the string to stay at the
same position.
All right? In that case, the energy
would change if you lifted the whole
string up or down.
So, we're we're talking about uh
translations of the uh of the phi
coordinate. So, it's the pinning down
which breaks the symmetry of phi goes to
phi plus a constant.
If we were talking about an infinite
string, we need to be talking I I should
have said we need to be talking about an
infinite string which is not pinned down
anywheres.
And that Lagrangian doesn't apply to the
finite string.
Well, there's something that breaks the
symmetry for the finite string, namely
the pinning down condition. There is
another situation. Here, let me invent a
different kind of string which really
does have the symmetry.
Let's imagine here we have a pole over
here
and a pole over here. There's a ring
over here. There's a ring over here that
can slide up and down the pole, and the
string is stretched between these two.
Okay?
All right. Now,
now you can shift the whole string
without any cost in energy.
You can't shift the whole string if the
ends are pinned are pinned down.
But if the ends are free to slide up and
down,
then it's a then there's a symmetry
which is the symmetry of translation of
the whole string. phi goes to phi plus a
constant. In that circumstance, the
integral of phi dot would be conserved.
And you know what the integral of phi
dot would be for this uh Remember what
phi is? It's just a vertical coordinate
of the string.
It would just be the whole ordinary
momentum of the string moving up and
down.
So, if you give the whole thing a push
up, it'll just continue to go up.
That's what it says.
Uh so, you have to be careful and make
sure that you really have the symmetry.
And you would not have the symmetry if
the ends of the string were pinned down,
but you do have the symmetry if the ends
of the string are free to move. Do you
know Do you know the term Dirichlet and
Neumann boundary conditions? Yeah, okay.
So,
for Dirichlet boundary conditions, that
means the string pinned down, you don't
have the symmetry. For Neumann
conditions, you do.
All right, but this was just an example.
Uh and it's not a terribly interesting
symmetry.
In particular,
if we had the term in the Lagrangian
plus
mu over two, there should be a one half
multiplying this.
Uh mu phi squared
minus mu phi squared,
then we no longer have the symmetry
because phi squared will not be
invariant when you shift phi. If you
shift phi, phi squared is not invariant.
It changes.
So, if we have this mu phi squared term,
we no longer have the symmetry. So, this
is not a very robust symmetry.
It's uh just a a particular case which
was very easy to illustrate. phi goes to
phi plus a constant.
And uh
as I said, it corresponds to a sort of
uniform center of mass motion of the
whole string vertically
along the phi axis.
But an ordinary field
uh in infinite space, an ordinary field
phi in infinite space, if it doesn't
have this mass term, where is it? If it
doesn't have the term that I call the
mass term here,
then it will also have a similar
symmetry.
Phi goes to phi plus a constant.
All right. Next time, I think uh I think
we're finished for today.
Uh next time we have to study
spatial momentum.
Ordinary momentum.
The stuff that when it hits you knocks
you on your
not
field momentum, but the kind of momentum
that really hits you
when a pulse of when a high-energy pulse
of radiation hits you, it gives you a
push,
and that's a different kind of momentum
than this field momentum.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.